<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certayne newes of the whole discription, ayde, and helpe of the Christian princes and nobles the vvhich for the comfort and deliueraunce of the poore Christians in the Low Countries, are gathered together, and are nouue vvith their armies in the fielde : drawen and copied out of a letter, sent vnto vs out of the same campe ... / translated out of Dutche into English, the 12. of April.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1574</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 13 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18670</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5182.2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1858</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22839065</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22839065</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25795</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18670)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25795)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1789:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certayne newes of the whole discription, ayde, and helpe of the Christian princes and nobles the vvhich for the comfort and deliueraunce of the poore Christians in the Low Countries, are gathered together, and are nouue vvith their armies in the fielde : drawen and copied out of a letter, sent vnto vs out of the same campe ... / translated out of Dutche into English, the 12. of April.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Dordrecht :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1574.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]⁴(-A1?) B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Lambeth Palace Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25795:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 56 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:25795:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 56 -->
            <p>CERTAYNE NEWES OF THE <hi>whole diſcription, ayde,</hi> and helpe of the Chriſtian Princes and Nobles, the vvhich for the comfort and deliueraunce of the poore Chriſtians in the low Countries, are gathered together, and are novve vvith their armies in the fielde.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Drawen and Copied out of a letter, ſent vnto vs out of the ſame Campe.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>¶ <hi>Apocal. 18. ver. 5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>For her ſinnes are gone vp to heauen, and God hath remembred her vvickedneſſe.</p>
               <p>Revvard her euen as ſhe revvarded you, and geue her double according to her vvorkes.</p>
               <p>And poure in double to her, in the ſame Cup vvhich ſhe filled vnto you.</p>
            </q>
            <p>¶ <hi>Printed at Dordrecht.</hi> 1574.</p>
            <p>¶ Tranſlated out of Dutche into English, the. 12. of April.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:25795:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 57 -->
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:25795:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 57 -->
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eloued Reader, wée finde in the olde and auncient Hiſtories &amp; Monuments, and that amongſt all other wiſe Monarchies &amp; kings, wee reade howe the great and mightie <hi>Caugniſta,</hi> king of Egypt, when he ſawe that he ſhould dye, he called vnto him his ſeuen ſonnes, and hauing a Quiuer of Arrowes bound in a bundel, commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them one after another to breake them in péeces, the which when it was not poſſible for them to do, he cauſed the bundel to be vnlooſed, and cauſed them to be ſcattered one from the other, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding eche of them to breake one of them, which then was very eaſie to be done: he wyllyng to teache his ſeuen ſonnes by this example, that if ſo be they were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided in the kingdome, &amp; kept not them ſelues within the bondes of vnitie and concorde, that then they eaſily ſhoulde be conſumed, broken in péeces, and thruſt out of their Empire. In like maner we reade of the olde <hi>Granduellis,</hi> howe hée left this for a Teſtament in his laſt will,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:25795:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 58 -->vnto that mightie Emperor <hi>Charles</hi> the fift, that if ſo be his Maieſtie woulde proſper in the Romaine Empyre accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his wyll, that then he ſhoulde en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour him ſelfe to the vttermoſt of his power, to raiſe all hatred and diſcorde to be betwéene the elected Princes, and the other Princes of the Empire, that in the meane time, while they were at ſtrife, and warred one with the other, then the Eagle might eate and deuour them all: this ſubtile practiſe hath that Antechriſt of Rome, this ſeuen yeres here in theſe lowe Countries, and about ten or twelue yeres in Fraunce, not without greate bloodſhedde and vtter ruine of both theſe Countries practiſed: And except that the Almightie God with his ſtrong arme had turned them from vs, that helliſhe Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, with the water that procéedeth out of his mouth, woulde haue drowned and deuoured vs vp: And that this was their practiſe, we may perceiue, for if they had once ouercome Fraunce, and theſe lowe Countries, they woulde procéede further, againſt all the Princes and Nobles vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:25795:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 58 -->the Empyre, which haue and dooe confeſſe the Goſpell, ſpoyling them of all dominion and libertie, yea, and of their liues alſo, as it may manifeſtlye appeare by the blooddy execution of that tyranniſh Counſell of Trent, and the Spaniſh In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition, which ſpareth neither Dukes, Earles, nor Lordes, of what ſtate ſoeuer they be, but againſt all promiſe, fayth, and fidelitie, like moſt wicked periurers, haue moſt pitiouſly murdered, beheaded, and taken their liues from them.</p>
            <p>By the which, through the illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God, there are mooued the chéefeſt Proteſtant Princes of the Romane Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyre, who foreſéeing what might come to paſſe, haue thought that if they ſhoulde nowe holde their peace and be ſtyll, and not aſſiſt their fellowe members of the faith, in the time of their néede, that then ſo ſoone as the tyraunt had quenched his yre in Fraunce, and in theſe lowe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, with ſheadding of Chriſtian blood, and murdering all Magiſtrates and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, vnto the which he aſpireth, that then hée woulde alſo procéede againſte
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:25795:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 59 -->them, and not put vp his blooddy ſworde into the Scabberde, tyll that he had rooted out of all landes, all thoſe that denie the Pope, and acknowledge Chriſt onely to be the head of the Church.</p>
            <p>And albeit that the godlye and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Magiſtrates knowe of a ſuretie, that Almightie GOD, with his mightie hande, can deliuer his Church, without the aſſiſtaunce of any man, neuertheleſſe we may finde in holy writyng, that God by his appoynted Magiſtrates, hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes defended the ſame, and ſpecially, howe the father of all the faithfull, our father <hi>Abraham,</hi> when hée heard that his brother <hi>Lot,</hi> and all his goodes and houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde were taken and caryed away cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, hée aroſe vp with all his power and purſued the enemyes and ſlewe them, &amp; deliuered thoſe that were taken with all theyr goodes, and reſtored to euery man his owne, ſo that if all examples that could bée ſhewed ſhould here bee brought in, it would bée tedious for the Chriſtian Reader: but this muſt wée wel note and vnderſtande, that God hath giuen the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:25795:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 59 -->ſworde into the Magiſtrates hand to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the good and innocent, and to puniſh the wicked and vngodlye, Yea, that moſt vnchriſtian Emperour <hi>Traianus,</hi> when hée ordained any Pretor, and gaue to him the ſword of iuſtice, would ſay thus vnto him, Vſe thy ſworde againſt mine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, in iuſt cauſes, and if I my ſelfe doo otherwiſe then iuſtice, vſe thy power vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon mée alſo.</p>
            <p>Let vs then Chriſtian Reader, geue thanks vnto the almighty God, who hath raiſed vp theſe godlye Princes and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, to be meanes for to deliuer his poore afflicted people, the which for theyr ſinnes, haue this while béene worthelye puniſhed.</p>
            <p>And therefore are we bound to pray to God from the bottom of our hearts, that hée wyll gouerne with his holye Spirite theſe Princes and Nobles, whiche are gathered nowe togeather for our ayde and comfort, that they maye in all theyr enterpriſes, ſeeke nothing elles but the glorye of God, the honour of his holye name, and the commodity of al Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:25795:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 60 -->and that the Deuilliſhe, Popiſhe, and Antechriſtian Kingdome may bée rooted out and vtterly deſtroyed. Amen.</p>
            <div n="princes and nobles" type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                  <hi>The diſcription of the</hi> Princes and Nobles which are nowe gathered togeather, and haue to their aduantage the Citie of Maſeike: where as it is nowe very co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modious for them to paſſe ouer the Maſe by Shippe into Brabant.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND therefore Chriſtian Reader, that</hi> thou mayeſt Prayſe the great and maruailous goodnes of God, who as hée hath the hearts of all Princes and gouernours in his hande, and hath not onely moued them to ayde and aſſyſt vs, but alſo hath made them willing to turne that great tyranny backe from vs, which truly the Pope by his enterpriſes would
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:25795:5"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 60 -->haue brought on vs, and all other Godly Chriſtians, in what Lande or dominion ſoeuer they were: wée haue therefore for your comfortes, cauſed theyr names, and Armies with theyr preparations of <hi>Rut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> and other Souldiers, here vnder to bée written, that ye thereby Chriſtian Reader might haue better entelligence thereof as followeth:</p>
               <p>Duke <hi>Magnus,</hi> brother vnto the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye and Renowmed King of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> a Noble man, and verye expeart in the Warres, hée amongeſt all other is cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen chiefe Generall of the fielde, and ouer all the reſt of the other, wyſe Marſhall Princes and Nobles, and hée hath vnder his owne gouernment. <hi>2500.</hi> Horſe, and <hi>4000.</hi> Gunners.</p>
               <p>Duke <hi>Hans Cazimirus,</hi> and <hi>Philip Land grane</hi> of <hi>Heſſen,</hi> they haue bothe <hi>1500.</hi> Horſe, and. <hi>10.</hi> Enſignes of Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diours.</p>
               <p>Duke <hi>Chriſtopher,</hi> Sonne vnto the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:25795:6"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 61 -->
                  <hi>Palſgraue,</hi> hath. <hi>2500,</hi> Horſe, and. <hi>4000.</hi> Gunners.</p>
               <p>Graue <hi>Lodwicke,</hi> Graue <hi>Iohn,</hi> Graue <hi>Hendrik</hi> of <hi>Naſſow,</hi> Brethren vnto the renowmed Prince of <hi>Orrange,</hi> they haue betwéene them. <hi>4000.</hi> Horſe, and. <hi>8000.</hi> Gunners.</p>
               <p>Item Graue <hi>Lodwick</hi> hath beſide theſe <hi>900.</hi> Light horſemen, and. <hi>2000.</hi> Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, which ſhoote with Corriers.</p>
               <p>Alſo there is the renowmed and Elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Prince, Duke <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> althoughe not in his owne perſon, yet with his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable aide, he is with the aforenamed Armye. And vnto theſe alſo are ioyned the Duke of <hi>Saxon,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>VVymeren,</hi> for that as yet they are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muſtered, we can adde no certaine num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="army" type="part">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:25795:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 61 -->
               <head>The other Armie.</head>
               <p>Beſydes theſe, <hi>Iulius</hi> Duke of <hi>Bruynſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick,</hi> a very Ritche and mightye Lorde, pitying the ſtate of the poore Chriſtians, and being one that hath a true loue vnto the Goſpell of Ieſu Chriſt, and a verye enemye vnto the Antechriſt of <hi>Rome,</hi> hath ioyned him ſelfe, and geuen his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to this great preparatyon of theſe Warres, and hath appointed the expert and couragious, Graue of <hi>Svvartzen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borch,</hi> ſo bée generall ouer his Armye, which doe gather them ſelues togeather in fielde betwéene <hi>Paterborne,</hi> and <hi>Soeſt</hi> in <hi>VVeſtphalen,</hi> and hath vnder his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment theſe that follow:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Manderſloe</hi> hath vnder his band. <hi>4000 Ruitters,</hi> and two bandes of Souldiours, and there followeth vnto theſe Armies daylye, many Barrons, Squyers, and Gentlemen, with other credible Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauntes and Citizens, the wich being
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:25795:7"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 62 -->moued with a Godly zeale, doo not here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſéeke anye of theyr owne profite or gaine, but rather the glorye of God, and the commoditye of the whole lande and Prouinces, &amp; that the conſciences of the poore captiues that are in <hi>Babilon,</hi> vnder the handes of that mighty Hunter <hi>Nem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod,</hi> which is the <hi>Pope</hi> of Rome, might bée deliuered.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>¶ The Concluſion.</head>
               <p>For as much beloued Reader, that the almighty God hath ſo mercifully appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto vs, and hath offered this his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent benefites &amp; helpe, Let vs not make ſmall account thereof, or lightlye regard it, but rather let vs with a Godly life and conuerſation, in prayer and thankes ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, attend and wayte on the good wyll &amp; pleaſure of God, not murmuring and ſaying, that the maintenance of ſo many <hi>Ruitters</hi> and ſouldiours doth impoueriſh, and bring the whole countrey into great miſerye, for this wée may aſſure our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, and therein take comfort, if ſo bée
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:25795:7"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 62 -->the Tyrant ſhoulde get the vpperhande, they wil not bee content with our Cities, Landes, goodes, and poſſeſſions, but they would force our Wiues, rauiſhe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file our Daughters, kyll our young men, murther our olde men and women, and with penurye and hunger, famiſhe our Children and ſucking Infantes, and ſo bring vs into ſuch an euerlaſting thral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and bondage, that wée ſhould haue wiſhed rather to haue died, if it were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible a thouſand times, then to lyue any longer in ſuch a myſerable captiuitye &amp; miſery. Therfore moſt deare chriſtians, let vs thinke, although wée are hindered a yere or two, of our goodes &amp; occupying, for to withſtand the enemye, wée know and hope notwithſtanding, that God by ſuch meanes wyll giue vnto vs his holy word and Goſpell, which is not to bée bought for any worldly goodes or treaſure: and for as muche as wée hope, that once within theſe fewe dayes, God wyll driue the Tyraunt away from vs, and bleſſe vs with all maner of bleſſinges, wée ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing godly and in his feare, our countrey
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:25795:8"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 63 -->ſhall proſper in all godlineſſe and other kynde of occupying, the which God graunt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs for his ſonne Chriſtes ſake. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.
<figure>
                  <q>BY THE STVDY OF LETTERS IMMORTALITY IS GOTTEN</q>
                  <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
                  <p>1573</p>
               </figure>
            </trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:25795:8"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 63 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
